BETH: The internet and mobile phones
mean bullying can now happen during
the day, when an individual is
mixing with others and when they
are in the safety of their own home.
Online or cyber bullying can be
via text messages, emails, online
gaming, chat rooms, instant
messaging and social networks.
Some autistic young people may need
extra support and guidance to stay
safe online and educational settings
have a duty and responsibility to
protect individuals in their care.
JOE: If an individual is being bullied
either at school or at work, then
it’s best to talk to them and find
out more, to see if help can be given.
They should be calmly listened to
making sure that they know they are
believed and it’s not their fault.
Some individuals with autism will
find it easier to write about the
incident or draw a picture about
what happened, and they could be
encouraged to keep a diary of events.
BETH: The individual may not realise
that they are being bullied and may need
this explained to them, differentiating
between being friendly or being a bully.
They should be told why behaviour
that hurts or harms them
emotionally or physically, is
not acceptable and is bullying.
JOE: An individual may show
sudden changes in behaviour,
which may be due to bullying.
This might be increased anxiety,
difficulty sleeping or outbursts at home.
A child may mimic the acts of bullies,
at home, by bullying their siblings
because they don't understand that this
behaviour is unacceptable, they are simply
acting out what their peers are doing.
BETH: Sometimes an individual
with autism may bully others.
This is more often not intentional
bullying, but a way of communicating
and trying to get attention.
It may be because they are being
told to do it by others, exploiting
their need to fit in, and they may
be unaware of the consequences,
and that they are hurting others.
JOE: Discussing and showing them the
consequences of their actions can help
them to understand what they are doing
is wrong and maybe linking it to what has
been done to them can help to show this.
BETH: The long-term effects of bullying
of individuals with autism can be
serious and they can end up with
long-lasting insecurities, behavioural
issues and low self-esteem, and
it can affect their concentration.
They may become more inclined to refuse
to take part in social situations because
they are afraid of being bullied or they
may experience stress-related illnesses.
JOE: If the bullying becomes really
serious and a potential criminal
offence is committed, it may be
necessary to contact the police.
Harassment and stalking, threats of harm
or violence to a person or property,
evidence of sexual exploitation such as
grooming and the distribution of sexual
images or inappropriate sexual contact
or behaviour are all criminal offences.
BETH: Addressing bullying issues as soon
as they are recognised and taking the
appropriate action, will help to reduce
the effects of bullying and exploitation
and hopefully reduce any long-term
issues that could be experienced.